<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian exercise, containing an easie entrance into the principles of religion and the chiefest points of our saluation in Christe, with a direction for all Christians, into the true seruice of God. By VV. Horne.</title>
            <author>Horne, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118318</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853525</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853525</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18910</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03700)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18910)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 891:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian exercise, containing an easie entrance into the principles of religion and the chiefest points of our saluation in Christe, with a direction for all Christians, into the true seruice of God. By VV. Horne.</title>
                  <author>Horne, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[54] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert VValde-graue, dwelling without Temple-barre, neere vnto Somerset house,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1585?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Not the same text as STC 20585.3.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁴ (-D4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Chriſtian exerciſe, <hi>Containing an eaſie entrance</hi> INTO THE PRINCIPLES OF RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the chiefest points of our ſaluation in Chriſte, with a direction for all Chriſtians, into the true ſeruice of God.</p>
            <p>By VV. HORNE.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>GOD JS MY DEFENDER</hi>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON; <hi>Printed by Robert <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de-<hi>graue, dwelling without</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-barre, neere vnto</hi> Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet houſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:2"/>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18910:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An eaſie entraunce into <hi>the principles of Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.3.</bibl>
               <p>This is life eternall, that they know thee to be the onely very God, and whome thou haſte ſent, Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.15.16.</bibl>
               <p>Be ready alwayes to giue an anſwere to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that asketh you a reaſon, of the hope that is to you, and that with meekneſſe &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Vho hath neade thée, and all things els?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Iſa. 44.2. pſal. 139 13.14. nihe. 9.6.</note> GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Ioh. 4.24. ier. 10.10. gen. 17.1. deut. 32.39. mat. 28.19. 1. ioh. 5.7.</note> A ſpirit, a knighty, &amp; eternal, one in eſſence, and yet three diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore hath he made thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To know him, and worſhip him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is he knowne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Pſal. 19.1. rom 1.20. ioh. 5.39. ioh. 4.24.</note> By his workes, and word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How muſt he be worſhipped?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpirite and trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is trueth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His holy word, conteyning the Law and the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the Law?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Exod. 20. deut. 5.6.7. mat. 22.37.38.39.</note> That which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended in the ten Commandementes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What requireth he of vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Loue to God, and loue to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18910:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is God to be loued?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With al the heart with al the ſoule, and with all the minde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is this knowne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Phil. 37.8. heb. 11.24.25</note> If we prefer his glory and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip before al thinges.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is our neighbour loued?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Math. 7.12.</note> If we doe to him as we would be done by.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth any man herein ſatiſfie the Law?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(3)" place="margin">Galat. 3.22.</note> No, and therefore all are conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(4)" place="margin">Deut. 27.26,</note> Becauſe it curſeth all that doe it not, and none do it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:4"/>
            <p>How are we then deliuered from the curſſe and bondage of the Law?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Galat. 4.4.5. gal. 3.13.</note> By Ieſus Chriſt that kept it, and was accurſed for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How knoweſt thou this?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the Goſpell?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> The power of God to ſaluation to euery beleeuer, proclayming forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(3)" place="margin">Math. 17.5. heb 1.2.3. luk. 1.11. heb. 1.9.</note> The ſonne of the liuing God, our ſauiour annoynted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why calleſt than him annoynted?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For that he is King, Prophete, and Prieſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why a King?</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18910:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Pſal. 26. luk. 1.32.33.</note> To raigne and rule ouer vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why is he a Prophete?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Math. 17.5. heb. 1.2.</note> To teach vs his fathers will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why is he a Prieſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(3)" place="margin">Heb. 9.1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For that he hath ſacrificed for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What hath he ſacrificed for vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That part of himſelfe that ſuffered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſuffered in Chriſts, his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, or manhood?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(4)" place="margin">Phil. 2.6.7.8. 1. Pet. 3.1ſt.</note> His Godhead can not ſuffer, it was therefore his manhood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſuffered he in ſoule?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(5)" place="margin">Math. 27 4<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. luk. 22.44.</note> Helliſh tormentes to acquite our ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſuffered he in body?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Math. 27.59 math 15.37. luk. 23.46.</note> Death temporal, to deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death eternall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I perceiue then, that he gaue body for body, and ſoule for ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He did ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How knowſt thou this to be for thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the certificate of Gods ſpirite, faith, and the Sacramentes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why, what doth Gods ſpirite?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> Certifie my ſpirite, that I am the ſonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(3)" place="margin">Act. 15.9. rom 10.10.</note> Purifie my hearte, aſſuring the ſame, that Chriſt with his merites is mine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is this?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(4)" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note> Al my ſins became his, &amp; his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes
<pb facs="tcp:18910:5"/>by imputation became mine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereof commeth this faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> By hearing, and hearing by the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is this faith increaſed &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the word preached, and by ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many Sacraments?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.1.2.3.4.</note> Two, Baptiſme, and the Lordes ſupper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the ſigne in Baptiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(3)" place="margin">Act. 8.36.</note> Water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the thing ſignified?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(4)" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.7</note> Chriſts blood, clenſing vs from al ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What benefit haue we by Baptiſme.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21. acts 2.41. acts. 2.38. rom. 6.6.</note> Incorporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viſible church, aſſuraunce of Gods promiſe: and that as water waſheth away all filthineſſe of body, ſo by Chriſte we are waſhed from all euill of body and ſoule, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs alſo our new byrth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth the Lordes ſupper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.26. acts. 2.42. 1. cor. 10.17.</note> Set out the Lordes death, ſeale vp Gods promiſe, and teache vs loue one with an other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What are the partes hereof?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(3)" place="margin">Math. 26.26. mat. 14.22.23. luk. 22.19.20. 1. Cor. 11.23.25.</note> Viſible ſignes, &amp; inuiſible graces?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What are the viſible ſignes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bread, and Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What are the inuiſible graces?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(4)" place="margin">Rom. 4.25. rom. 5.9.</note> Ful redemption and iuſtification by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why is there vſed both Bread and
<pb facs="tcp:18910:6"/>Wine?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Ioh. 6.55.56</note> To teach vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt is our meat, and Chriſt is our drinke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bread then is not Chriſtes body?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Act. 3.21. luk. 22.19. heb. 10.14.</note> No, for bodily the heauens holde him til the day of the reſurrection of all thinges, but it repreſents his body, as the mine doth his blood, ſhewing, that by one oblation he hath conſecrated for euer them that are ſanctified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why then, Maſſes are blaſphemous, and Maſſemongers and ſuch as ſeeke ſaluation by workes blaſphemers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are ſo, for that they reſt not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this onely ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet the workes muſt be done?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(3)" place="margin">Ephe. 2.10. luk. 17.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> I grant ſo, but not our will works, but ſuch as God hath commanded, and then to haue no truſt in them: ſo when we haue done all we can, we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruants.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How muſt we come to the ſupper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28. 2 cor 7.10 galat. 6.15. 2. cor. 13.5. 1. cor. 10.17. math. 26.30. math. 14.26.</note> Firſt in examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſelues, whether we haue a Godly ſorrow for our ſinnes paſt, and purpoſe of new life. 2. Whether we haue faith to take hold of Chriſt and his righteouſneſſe. 3. Whether we haue loue, declaring vs one body. 4. Whether thankfulnes to God for his benefites.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence commeth it if we ſo come?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Iac. 1 17. ioh. 16.23. 1 cor 11.9. 1. cor. 11.33. 1. cor. 14.16.</note> Of the grace of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is that obtayned?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By prayer made in Chriſtes name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then, that we eate not, or drink not vnworthily, and ſo haue damnation, it is good we come together in prayer, ioyning with the Minſter in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; that we worthily take it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God graunt vs ſo to do. Amen.</p>
            <signed>W. HORNE.</signed>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:7"/>
            <head>A moſte eaſy and plaine instruction for all Christians.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Vhether arte thou a ſinner or not</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am a ſinner, &amp; by nature a<note n="(1)" place="margin">Rom. 3.9. eph. 2.1.3. 1 Iohn. 1.8.</note> childe of wrath moſt worthie of eternal damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How becameſt thou a ſinner, and childe of wrath?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the fal and tranſgreſſion<note n="(2)" place="margin">Gen 3.6.</note> of <hi>Adam:</hi>
               <note n="(3)" place="margin">Pſal 51.5. rom. 5.12.</note> for we comming of him that was corrupt are corrupt as he was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sinne is the tranſgreſſion of the<note n="(4)" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.4.15.</note> law of God:<note n="(5)" place="margin">Mat. 5.22.27. &amp; 12.36. iam. 3.2.</note> be it either by thought, word, or deede.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what means commeth the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the law<note n="(1)" place="margin">Rom 5.20. &amp; 7.7.</note> of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the reward of ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The rewarde of ſinne,<note n="(2)" place="margin">Rom. 6.23. math. 25.41.</note> is eternall death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the remedy and meanes to be deliuered from that eternall death which ſinne deſerueth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(3)" place="margin">Ioh. 14.6.25.</note> Onely our Lord and ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,<note n="(4)" place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> who hath dyed to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from our ſinnes, and roſe againe to iuſtifie vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what means ſhal we know that the death of Chriſt is profitable for vs to deliuer vs from our ſins, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile vs to God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(5)" place="margin">Ioh. 6.3.16. acts. 13.39. rom. 3.25.</note> By faith which Gods ſpirit wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in our hearts.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the means to come to faith, whereby we apprehend Ieſus Chriſte with his righteouſneſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Rom. 10.17. acts. 2.37.38.41. 1. cor. 4.15.</note> The means to come to faith, and to haue the ſame increaſe in vs: is the miniſtery of the worde or Goſpell of God and the Sacraments, with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall and hearty prayer to God for his grace and bleſſing in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing that by the law commeth the knowledge of ſinne: and the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, containe the ſumme of the law: it ſhall be profitable to know what ſinnes the Lord condemneth and forbiddeth, and what vertue he requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in each commaundement. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſe the commaundements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Exod. 20. deut. 5.</note> Heare O Iſrael, I am the lord thy God which brought thee out of the land of Egipt, and out of the houſe of bondage, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth the Lorde teach vs by
<pb facs="tcp:18910:9"/>this preface?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that he ſaith<note n="(1)" place="margin">Gen. 17.1. leuit. 19.12. &amp;. 20.17. deut. 32.39.</note> I am the Lord thy God: he ſheweth his almighty power and excellent maieſtie. Alſo the high authoritie hee hath ouer his people. And when he ſayth, he brought them out of the land of<note n="(2)" place="margin">Eſai. 1.2. &amp; 5. 4. ezek 16. rom. 2.4.</note> Egipt, and out of the houſe of bondage. He ſetteth foorth his infinite goodneſſe, and ſo giueth a reaſon to ſtir vp the people of Iſrael vnto the obedience of his lawes: vnles they will ſhew them ſelues, both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and diſobedient to his power and authoritie, and vnthankfull for his goodnes. So<note n="(3)" place="margin">Rom. 9.25. 1. pet. 2.10.</note> now ſeeing the lord hath deliuered vs out of the bondage of ſinne, and from the tyrannie of the Deuill, and bleſſeth vs with his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfold benefites, both for our bodyes and ſoules: the ſame reaſon ſerueth no leſſe for vs then it did for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the firſt commaundement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods before me.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth the Lorde requyre of vs in this commaundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that we ſhoulde acknowledge him to be the<note n="(1)" place="margin">Iam. 1 17.</note> fountaine and giuer of all good thinges,<note n="(2)" place="margin">Pſa. 115.3.135.6. eph. 1.11.</note> and the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and gouernour of all things. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,<note n="(3)" place="margin">Deut. 10.12. mal. 1.6.</note> that we feare, reuerence, and loue him aboue all things. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our<note n="(4)" place="margin">Ier. 17.7. eph. 1.12.13.</note> truſt and confidence be fixed and ſtayed in him onely. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that we<note n="(5)" place="margin">Pſal. 50.15. rom. 10.12. iam. 1.5.</note> call vpon him in faith: for what ſoeuer thinges we ſtande in need of, either for our ſoules or bodies. Fiftly, that we<note n="(6)" place="margin">Pſal. 50.14. ephe. 5.20. theſ. 5.18. heb. 13.15.</note> be thankful to him for all his giftes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſinnes doth the Lorde forbid and condemn in this commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All thoſe which bee contrary to the vertues required. As not to<note n="(7)" place="margin">Eſai. 31.1.2. ie. 17.5. &amp; 48 7.</note> acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge him to be the fountaine and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of all good-thinges, the preſeruer and gouernour of all thinges, or to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the ſame to anye other, or to
<pb facs="tcp:18910:10"/>tranſfer that fear, reuerence, and loue, truſt or confidence, that is due to God: to any thing els; whatſoeuer it be, or in our neceſſity to call vppon any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the ſecond commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, nor the likenes of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, nor in the water vnder the earth: thou ſhalt not bowe downe to them nor worſhip them, for I the Lord thy God am a ielous God, and viſite the ſinnes of the fathers vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Children vnto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhew mercy vnto thouſandes of them that loue me, and keepe my commaundements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſin doth God forbid and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne in this commaundement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we ſhoulde thinke God to be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18910:10"/>like either man or woman, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creature whatſoeuer it be<note n="(1)" place="margin">Deu. 4.15.16 eſa. 40.18. 1. tim. 6.16.</note> and therefore, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we make no image of God to expreſſe him by. Secondly, that we make no image of any other thing, for religion, either to worſhip<note n="(2)" place="margin">Exo. 32. pſa 97.7. &amp; 106.36.</note> the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage it ſelf, either God, ſaint, or angel by the image, neither yet to this ende to be the better put in mind of God by the image.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth God require of vs in this commaundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we ſhould worſhip God<note n="(3)" place="margin">Ioh. 4.23. deut. 5.32.12 32.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his worde and ordinaunce, and not after<note n="(4)" place="margin">Eſay. 29 13. mat. 15.9.</note> our fantasies or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes of men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What haue we to learne by the the addition?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſame the Lorde doth ſtirre vs to the obedience of his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes by a dubble reaſon, of the one ſide to flye ſinne, for<note n="(5)" place="margin">Exod. 34.7. Leuit. 26.14. deut. 28.15. luk. 13.3.</note> feare of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and on the other to follow vertue
<pb facs="tcp:18910:11"/>for the<note n="(1)" place="margin">Leuit. 26.3. deut. 28.1. eſai. 1.19. mat 5.3.7.</note> promiſe of his mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the third commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lorde thy God in vaine, for the Lorde will not holde him guiltleſſe that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his name in vaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth God forbid in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord in this commaundement forbiddeth and condemneth al<note n="(2)" place="margin">Leuit. 24.11.14.16.</note> blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming of the name of God, all<note n="(3)" place="margin">Leuit. 19.12 zach. 5.3. mal. 3.5.</note> periury or forſwearing, and al vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or vaine ſwearing, be it by the name of God directly, or indirectly by his<note n="(4)" place="margin">Math. 5.34. &amp; 23.22.</note> creatures, and all abuſe of his holy name, by<note n="(5)" place="margin">Exod. 22.18. micha. 5.12. mal. 3.5.</note> witchcraft, ſorcery, or charming, or curſed ſpeaking, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe to thinke or ſpeak of the name of God without great reuerence of his maieſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth the Lord require of vs in this commaundement?</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18910:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That whenſoeuer we be required to take an othe for confirmation of truth, to the glory of God, or the profit of our brethren, we ſhould with al reuerence call<note n="(1)" place="margin">Deut. 6.13. iere. 4.2. heb. 6.16.</note> God to witneſſe for the truth, and that when we either ſpeake or thinke of him we ſhould do it with all<note n="(2)" place="margin">Iere. 10.6.7. pſalm. 8.1.</note> reuerence of his maieſty. And to ſtirre vs to fly theſe euils, and to moue vs to vſe his holye name in all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: he threatneth that he will not holde him guiltleſſe, that taketh his name in vaine, but culpable of the<note n="(3)" place="margin">Deu. 28.26.27.</note> curſſe of God and eternall damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the fourth Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember thou keepe holy the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day. Sixe dayes ſhalt thou labour and do all that thou haſt to do. But the ſeuenth day is the ſabboth of the Lord thy God. In it thou ſhalt do no maner of worke, thou, and thy ſome and thy daughter, thy man ſeruaunt, and thy mayde ſeruaunt, thy cattell, and the
<pb facs="tcp:18910:12"/>ſtraunger, that is with in thy gates. For in ſixe dayes the Lorde made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, the ſea, and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeuenth day. Wherefore the Lorde bleſſed the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day, and hollowed it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth the Lord require of vs in this commaundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we ſhould ſanctifie the ſabboth day, in<note n="(1)" place="margin">Exo. 16.26. deut. 5.4.</note> reſting from our owne bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie labours in worldly thinges. And in one place to aſſemble our ſelues togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with feare and reuerence,<note n="(2)" place="margin">Math. 13.54 luk 4.16. acts. 20.7.</note> to heare, marke, and lay vp in our harts, the worde of God preached and taught vnto vs. And to pray<note n="(3)" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.15.</note> togeather, in one conſent &amp; vnity of ſpirite. And at the times appointed to vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <note n="(4)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23.28.29.</note> ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in faith and repentaunce. And all our life to reſt from<note n="(5)" place="margin">Heb. 4.9.10 11.</note> wickednes: that the Lorde by his holy ſpirite may worke in vs, his good worke: that ſo we may begin in this life, the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting reſt.<note n="(6)" place="margin">Exo. 20. deut. 5.</note> To ſtirre vs vnto theſe dueties the Lorde ſetteth forth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18910:12"/>of his owne reſt. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the fift commandement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Honour thy father and thy mother that thy dayes may belong in the land which the Lord thy God giueth thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What vnderſtandeſt thou by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Feare, reuerence, and loue, ſhewed foorthe<note n="(1)" place="margin">Leu. 19.3. eph. 6.1. colo. 3.10.</note> by obedience to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, by aſſiſting them in al good: &amp; by<note n="(2)" place="margin">Mat. 15.6.</note> rereleeuing them in their neceſſities. The vices contrary are condemned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What vnderſtande you by father and mother?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not onely natural parents, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all<note n="(3)" place="margin">Exo. 22.28. leu. 19.32. rom. 13.1.</note> magiſtrates and gouernours, paſtours or miniſters, and ſcholemai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,<note n="(4)" place="margin">Eph. 5.6. col. 3.28.</note> maiſters of houſholdes, and all ſuperiours ordeined of God, to the defending and guiding of their inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.
<pb facs="tcp:18910:13"/>To ſtirre them to the obedience of this commaundement, the Lord ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his promiſe to bleſſe them with long life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the ſixt commandement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt do no murther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth the Lorde forbid and condemne in this commaundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord in this commandement forbiddeth not onely all vnlawful<note n="(1)" place="margin">Gen 9.6.</note> murther or killing in act: but alſo all hatred,<note n="(2)" place="margin">Leuit. 19.17.18. mat. 5.22 1. iohn. 3.15.</note> malice, anger, and all deſire of vengeance. And all quarelling, figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, mocks and taunts, proceeding of the ſame, and all occaſions of prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to anger. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is required in this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we ſhould<note n="(3)" place="margin">Math. 5.44. rom. 12.17.18.19.</note> loue our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures as our ſelues: which muſt be ſhewed in care to preſerue life, in hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb facs="tcp:18910:13"/>releeuing and comſorting one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the ſeuenth commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth the Lorde forbid and condemne in this commaundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not onely al adultery and fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and vnlawful ſociety of man and woman<note n="(1)" place="margin">Leui. 18.20. &amp; 20.10. deut. 23.17.</note> in act: but alſo all vnchaſte<note n="(2)" place="margin">Math. 5.28.</note> thoughts and vnlawful luſts of the hart, and al occaſions that might ſerue to prouoke thereunto,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is required in this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we ſhould lead our liues in all<note n="(3)" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.15.19. 1. theſ. 4.4.</note> chaſtity both in ſoules and bodyes, as pure Temples of the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is the eight Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth God forbid and condemn in this commaundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſte all robbing and ſtealing in acte.<note n="(1)" place="margin">Leu. 19.11.</note> Secondly all extorcion and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.<note n="(2)" place="margin">1. The 4.6. eph. 4.28.</note> Thirdly all deceipte in bying and ſelling,<note n="(3)" place="margin">Ephe. 3.5.</note> and vnlawfull deſire to enrich our ſelues with hurt or loſſe of our neighbours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is required of vs in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſte that we bee<note n="(4)" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.6.</note> content with that portion which God hach giuen vs, not ſeeking to augment it by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull meanes. Secondly, that euery one of vs<note n="(5)" place="margin">2. The. 3.10.</note> trauell faithfully in his calling. Thirdly, to be<note n="(6)" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.18. eph. 4.28. heb. 13 16.</note> helpfull to them that neede.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is the ninth Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:14"/>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witnes againſt thy neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is forbidden and condemned in this commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, wee are forbidden to ſpeake falſely in<note n="(1)" place="margin">Exo. 23.1. pio. 19.5.</note> iudgement when wee be requires to beare witneſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, all<note n="(2)" place="margin">Pſal. 15.3. ephe. 4.25.</note> backbiting of any man, al lying, flattering or diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is forbidden to ſpeake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of our brethren for priuate offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,<note n="(3)" place="margin">Math. 18.15.</note> if by priuate admonitions they may be won.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is required of vs in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vertues which bee contrary to theſe vices, as to ſpeake truth, in wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bearing, &amp; to haue like regard to the<note n="(4)" place="margin">Mat. 7.12.</note> credite of others as we woulde they ſhould haue of ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is the tenth Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbors houſe, thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wife, his ſeruaunt, his mayde, his ore, his aſſe, nor any thing that is his.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth the Lord forbid and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne in this commaundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All euill thoughtes, light motions,<note n="(1)" place="margin">Pſal. 19.12. rom. 7.7.</note> &amp; ſuddaine affections, and ſheweth that though we neuer purpoſe them, nor yet willingly conſent to them, yet they are ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth the Lorde require of vs in this commaundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That our conſciences and the verye<note n="(2)" place="margin">Pſal. 51.6. 1. cor. 7.1. ephe. 4.24.</note> thoughtes of our heartes be kept vpright before the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What vnderſtand you by this word neighbour?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:15"/>
            <p>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſheweth<note n="(1)" place="margin">Luk. 10.30</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all people be they friendes or enemies, familier with vs or ſtraungers, are to be eſteemed our neighbours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the ſumme of this law?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is this in few words as<note n="(2)" place="margin">Mat. 22.37.</note> Chriſt teacheth vs. Firſt thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy ſoule, and with all thy minde. Secondly, and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is any man able to keepe theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements as God requyreth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man<note n="(3)" place="margin">Iob. 4.18.19 &amp; 15.15. rom. 3.10.</note> hath, can, or ſhal, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Ieſus Chriſte who hath fulfilled them: and by his obedience,<note n="(4)" place="margin">Acts. 13.39. rom. 3.24. &amp; 10.4.</note> all that beleeue in him are iuſtified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If no man can keepe this Law, nor be iuſtified thereby: what profite haue Chriſtians by the knowledge of the ſame?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:16"/>
            <p>Firſt, it is to the Children of God a true<note n="(1)" place="margin">Pſal. 1.2. &amp; 219.1.9.</note> rule of righteouſneſſe, To teach them how they ought to walke. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it teacheth man to caſt<note n="(2)" place="margin">Rom. 3.4.23</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ff al truſt or confidence in his owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. Thirdly;<note n="(3)" place="margin">Rom. 3.19.</note> it <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the pride of man and humbleth him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. Fourthly, hauing ſhewed vs our miſery, it is<note n="(4)" place="margin">Galat. 3.24.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſchoolemaſter to direct vs vnto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What woorkes are acceptable to God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe which bee ruled and done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the<note n="(5)" place="margin">Deut. 12.28.32. math. 19.16.</note> word of God, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from a heart<note n="(6)" place="margin">Rom. 14.23. heb. 11.6.</note> purged by faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can thoſe workes iuſtifie vs before God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, for that were to deny the<note n="(7)" place="margin">Galat. 5.4.</note> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore then ſhoulde we doe good workes: ſeeing we are not iuſtified by them?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt to ſhew our loue<note n="(1)" place="margin">Iohn. 14.19. math. 5.16.</note> to God in glorifiyng of him as becommeth his children. Secondly, to profite our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to<note n="(2)" place="margin">Math. 15. heb. 13.</note> help the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their neceſſities and to win<note n="(3)" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.1. &amp; 3.1.</note> them by our good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of life. Thirdly, to giue teſtimony of our faith<note n="(4)" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10.</note> &amp; election by the fruites and effects thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faith is an aſſured<note n="(5)" place="margin">Rom. 4.3.13 heb. 10.22. &amp; 11.1.</note> perſwaſion of Gods fatherly good will towards vs, grounded vpon his free promiſes<note n="(6)" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.20.</note> in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where is it planted?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the heart.<note n="(7)" place="margin">Rom. 10 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By whom is faith wrought in man?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the holy Ghoſt.<note n="(8)" place="margin">Eph. 1.13. &amp; 3.16.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What profit haue we by faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:17"/>
            <p>I am aſſured by it, that al<note n="(1)" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Chriſtes paſſion and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, is as ſurely mine, as if I had wrought them my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the ſumme of this faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beleeue in God the father almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie maker of heauen and earth. And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely begotten ſonne our Lord, which was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin Mary. He ſuffred vnder Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cious Pilate, was crucified, dead and buried. He deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into hell, and the third day he roſe againe from death, hee aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the father almighty. From thence he ſhall come to iudge both the quicke and the dead. I beléeue in the holy ghoſt. The holy catholique church, the communion of ſaintes, the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, the reſurrection of the body, and the life euerlaſting. So be it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many partes are contayned in this confeſſion?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Foure, the firſte concerning God the Father. The ſecond, concerning God the Sonne. The third, concerning God the holy Ghoſt. The fourth concerning Gods people called the church, and the giftes of God to the ſame Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What do you learne in the firſt part?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that God who is almighty and maker of heauen and earth, and<note n="(1)" place="margin">Iohn. 1.12. rom. 8.14.15 16. gal. 3.26.</note> all that therein is: is my father and I his child by grace in Chriſt Ieſus. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he being almighty and Lord of all, and I his Child, he both can, and will, defend and keepe me, and prouide for me that I ſhall<note n="(2)" place="margin">Pſal. 34.9.10 mat. 6.32. rom. 6.27.28</note> lack nothing, that he ſeeth to be good for me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What learne you in the ſecond part?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in that hee is called Ieſus, I learne, that he is the<note n="(3)" place="margin">Math. 1.21.</note> ſauiour, to ſaue his people from their ſinnes. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in that he is called Chriſt which is annoynted, he is a<note n="(4)" place="margin">Dan. 7.14. luk. 1.33.</note> king to raigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:18910:18"/>his Church for euer, and a<note n="(1)" place="margin">Deu. 18.15. act 3.22.</note> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to teach his fathers will perfectly. And a Prieſt to offer him ſelfe<note n="(2)" place="margin">Pſa. 110.4. heb. 1.3. &amp; 9 14.</note> in ſacrifice, for the ſinnes of the people. The which were figured by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting of Kinges, Prophetes and Prieſtes vnder the law.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when I acknowledge him to be the onely ſonne of God: I learn that hee is<note n="(3)" place="margin">Eſay. 9.6. rom. 9.5. phil. 2.6.</note> God equall with the father from euerlaſting: and therefore able<note n="(4)" place="margin">Iohn. 3.16. heb. 9.14.28 &amp; 10.12.13.</note> to beare what ſo euer was due for our ſinnes, and of power to ſaue thoſe that truſt in him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, by his miraculous concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the holy Ghoſt, in the wombe of the Virgin: I learn that he is Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias<note n="(5)" place="margin">Eſay. 7.14.</note> &amp; Emmanuel which was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde by the Prophet <hi>Eſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, in that hee was borne of the Virgin Mary of the ſeed of <hi>Dauid:</hi> I learn that he was<note n="(6)" place="margin">Heb. 2.11. &amp; 14.4.15.</note> man in al things like to vs except ſinne. And therfore<note n="(7)" place="margin">Heb. 2.14.18 &amp; 4,15.16.</note> is ready to haue compaſſion of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, and to ſuccour thoſe that are tempted, and to beare what ſo euer is due to vs.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18910:18"/>
            <p>Sixtly, when it is ſaid, he ſuffered vnder Poncious Pilate, was crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, deade and buried, and deſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell: I learne that our Lorde and ſauiour, willingly, tooke vpon himſelfe our ſinnes and became a<note n="(1)" place="margin">Galat. 3.13.</note> curſſe for vs, that we by him might be deliuered from the curſſe due to vs for ſin.</p>
            <p>He alſo ſuffered a moſt ſhameful death and condemnation before men: to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer<note n="(2)" place="margin">Rom. 4.25. &amp; 5.6.10. &amp; 8.1.</note> vs from death and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before God. He hath bene made a<note n="(3)" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note> ſacrifice for ſin: that through him we might bee made righteous before God. And hath by vertue of his death deſtroyed the<note n="(4)" place="margin">Rom. 6.11. 1. Pet. 4.1.</note> power of ſinne in his members.</p>
            <p>And he was buried for a confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the trueth of his death. And when it is ſayde, hee deſcended into hell: I learne that he ſuffered not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the torments of body due to our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes: but alſo the torment and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhe<note n="(5)" place="margin">Eſay. 53:10. luk 22.44. mat. 27.46.</note> of ſoule and conſcience to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer our ſoules yea that he hath hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him ſelfe to beare the payne and tormentes of hell for the tyme, for our
<pb facs="tcp:18910:19"/>ſaluation.</p>
            <p>In that Chriſt roſe againe the third day from the dead. Firſt I learne that he hath<note n="(1)" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.57. rom. 4.25.</note> ouercome death and hell for my iuſtification.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I learne to riſe from ſin,<note n="(2)" place="margin">Rom. 6.4. col. 3.1.</note> to follow righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by the reſurrection of chriſt we haue a gage and teſtimony of our reſurrection, that we ſhal<note n="(3)" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.16</note> riſe again at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>In that he is aſcended, into heauen: I learne that his aſcention is a pledge to vs, that we ſhal aſcend<note n="(4)" place="margin">Iohn. 14.3.</note> after him thither where he is.</p>
            <p>And in that he ſitteth at the right hand of God. I learne that al power is giuen vnto him in heaueu and earth, and that he al<note n="(5)" place="margin">Mat. 28.18. ephe. 1.20.</note> creatures ſubiect vnto him, &amp; that he<note n="(6)" place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> maketh interceſſion for vs.</p>
            <p>In that which he ſayde: that Chriſt ſhal come to iudge the quicke and dead. Firſt, I learn, that he which<note n="(7)" place="margin">Iob. 19.25. math. 19.28.</note> ſhal be iudge is our ſauiour: and therefore his comming ſhal be for our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to the<note n="(8)" place="margin">2. The. 1.8. rom. 1.7. math. 25.41.</note> terrour of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18910:19"/>that he ſhal be their iudge whom they haue refuſed and diſpiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What learne you in the third part?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I learne that the holy Ghoſt, is very God<note n="(1)" place="margin">Mat. 28 19. ioh. 14.26.</note> equall with the father and the ſonne: and that he printeth in our harts the<note n="(2)" place="margin">Eph 1.13. &amp; 4.30.</note> promiſes of God made vnto vs in Ieſus Chriſt, and beareth<note n="(3)" place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> witneſſe to our ſpirits that we are the children of God. And worketh in vs the<note n="(4)" place="margin">Rom. 8,10. ephe. 4.23.</note> hatred of ſinne: &amp; ſtirreth vs vp to holineſſe of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What learne you in the fourth part?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſte I acknowledge and beleeue that God hath a Catholique, that is to ſay, an<note n="(5)" place="margin">Mat. 28.19. act 10.35.</note> vniuerſal Church: which is the number of Gods elect<note n="(6)" place="margin">1. Kin. 19.18. rom. 11.4. ephe. 1.4.</note> people, that he hath choſen out of al Nations to eternal life, and<note n="(7)" place="margin">Eph. 5.26.12</note> ſanctified in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. And in this Church there is a<note n="(8)" place="margin">1. Cor. 12. eph. 4.13.</note> communion and fellowſhip of Saintes, and true faithful people: all which the Lord<note n="(9)" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19.</note> knoweth to be his,
<pb facs="tcp:18910:20"/>of which number, I beleeue my ſelfe to be one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What difference is there betweene the inuiſible Church and the viſible?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The inuiſible Church comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all the electe of God from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the worlds vnto the ende thereof. And the viſible Church are thoſe that yet remayne in this vale of miſery, holding the profeſſion of faith and the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now the markes to know the viſible Church are, the true<note n="(1)" place="margin">Math. 28.19.</note> preaching of the Goſpel or worde of God, the right adminiſtration of the<note n="(2)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23.</note> ſacraments,<note n="(3)" place="margin">2. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note> and diſcipline.</p>
            <p>In theſe wordes the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: I learne, that both I my ſelfe,<note n="(4)" place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.7. reui. 1.6.</note> and al that truely beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, are ſo waſhed and clenſed from their ſinnes, and haue them ſo forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in Chriſt, that they ſhall<note n="(5)" place="margin">Iete. 31.31. heb. 8.12.</note> neuer be layd vnto their charge.</p>
            <p>And in theſe wordes, the reſurrection of the body and the life euerlaſting. I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18910:20"/>learne that theſe mortall bodyes of the faithfull,<note n="(1)" place="margin">Iob. 19.25. dan. 12.2. i. cor. 15.42.</note> ſhall be rayſed vp at the laſt day, and ſhall be couered againe with their ſkin, and ſhal be made like to the glorious body of Ieſus<note n="(2)" place="margin">Phil. 3.22. dani. 12.3.</note> chriſt according to his mightye working, whereby he is able to ſubdue al things vnto him ſelfe. And after this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, ſhall enioy<note n="(3)" place="margin">Math. 25.46. col. 3.4.</note> euerlaſting life with Chriſte in the glory of his Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what meanes is this faith main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, increaſed and ſtrengthened in vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ordinay meanes are. Firſt the<note n="(4)" place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> preaching of the word, as is the ſhewed before. Secondly, the true vſe of the<note n="(5)" place="margin">Mat. 26.26. &amp; 28.29.</note> ſacraments.<note n="(6)" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.5.</note> Thirdly, diſcipline. The<note n="(7)" place="margin">Mat. 6.6. mar. 11.24.</note> fourth earneſt prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is a ſacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sacrament is a viſible ſigne or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned<note n="(8)" place="margin">Mat. 28.19. mat. 26.26. mar. 1.4. 1. cor. 11.26.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God to confirme our faith in the truth of his promiſes,
<pb facs="tcp:18910:21"/>concerning his inuiſible graces, in Chriſt Ieſus, with a mutuall prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the honour that we beare vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many ſacraments hath Chriſt ordayned in his Church?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two, Baptiſme, and<note n="(1)" place="margin">Math. 28.19. &amp; 26.26.</note> the ſupper of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many parts are there in a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two, the outward ſigne, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the outward ſigne in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Mat. 3.11.</note> Water, wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partie to be baptiſed is dipped or ſprinckled: in the name<note n="(3)" place="margin">Math. 28.19.</note> of the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the inuiſible grace in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it ſignifieth, that as our bodies are waſhed with water: ſo our<note n="(1)" place="margin">Mar. 1.4. acts. 2.38.</note> ſins are waſhed away, and forgiuen vs by the bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſetteth before vs our regeneration<note n="(2)" place="margin">Rom. 6.3.4. tit 2.5.</note> or ſpirituall newe birth, to be ſhewed forth in dying vnto ſinne, and riſing to newneſſe of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the outwarde ſigne in the Lordes ſupper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bread and wine<note n="(3)" place="margin">Mat. 26.26.27.</note> both of which the Lord hath expreſly commanded al to receiue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the inuiſible grace ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the bread and wine?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The body<note n="(4)" place="margin">Luke. 22.19. 1. cor. 11.25.</note> of Chriſte broken and his bloud ſhed for vs, together with al the benefites of his paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward ſignes receiued?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are receiued with the hande,
<pb facs="tcp:18910:22"/>eaten<note n="(1)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.14</note> with the mouth, and diſge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the ſtomack.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How are the inuiſible graces recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are receiued onely by<note n="(2)" place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.53.54.55.</note> faith, whereby we feed of them, as of a foode, giuen vs of euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why did God chooſe thoſe creatures of Bread and Wine, to repreſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, the bodye and blood of Chriſte, rather then anye other earthly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe there are none other earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly creatures that can ſo aptly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto our outwarde ſenſes, thoſe thinges that God woulde haue vs to learne by this ſacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What be thoſe thinges which God would haue vs to learne by this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the<note n="(3)" place="margin">Mat. 26.27. mar. 14.15. luk. 22.23..</note> breaking of the bread, we
<pb facs="tcp:18910:22"/>haue to learne: the breaking of the body of Chriſt vpon the Croſſe, and by the pouring forth of the wine, the ſheading of his blood. And by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing to all that are preſent: Chriſtes<note n="(1)" place="margin">Ioh. 6.55.56.57. 1. cor. 10.16.</note> communicating him ſelfe to all that will faithfully receiue him.</p>
            <p>By the eating and drinking, wee learne: that as Bread and Wine doe nouriſhe our bodyes in this life: So Chriſtes body and blood<note n="(2)" place="margin">Ioh. 6.57. ioh. 15.4.</note>, do nouriſh our ſoules to life euerlaſting. And as the ſubſtaunce of Breade and Wine, by diſgeſtion paſſeth into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of our bodyes, euen ſo by faith, Chriſt and we are vnited with an vnſpeakable vnion, and made fleſhe of his fleſhe,<note n="(3)" place="margin">Eph. 5.30.</note> and bone of his bones, And that as of manye grayne is made one loaſe, and of many grapes one wine:<note n="(4)" place="margin">Cor. 10.17.</note> ſo we being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye are one body in Chriſt, and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally members one of an other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is the Breade and Wine tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the bodye and Bloode of Chriſt?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, for if you take awaye the ſigne that may be ſeene: it is no ſacrament, for there is no ſacrament without a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſigne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as much as the vnworthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers are guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt, and do<note n="(1)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.29.</note> eate and drinke their owne damnation as <hi>Saint Paule</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth. What is required of vs to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiuers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To examine<note n="(2)" place="margin">1. cor. 11.28.</note> our ſelues whether we be true members of Chriſt or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what tokens ſhal we know this?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt if we hartely<note n="(3)" place="margin">Eſai. 1.16. ioel. 2.12 13. 1. cor 11.18.20.</note> repent vs of our ſinnes, by an earneſt ſorrow and deſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame, with an earneſt mind and determinate purpoſe to lead our liues Godly hereafter. Next if we ſtay our ſelues and reſt in<note n="(4)" place="margin">Mar. 16.16. heb. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.22. &amp; 11.6.</note> a ſure hope and true faith of Gods mercy thorow Chriſt, with a thankful remembrance of our redemptiom, purchaſed by his
<pb facs="tcp:18910:23"/>death. And finally, ſeeing in the Lords ſupper is contained a token<note n="(1)" place="margin">Eſai. 1.17. mat. 5.23.24 Iohn. 13.34.</note> of frind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and loue among men, we beare bretherly loue to our neighbours, that is to all men, without any euill wil or hatred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is diſcipline?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is, the orderly<note n="(2)" place="margin">Math. 18.15. &amp;. 20.</note> gouernment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehentions and corrections vſed in the Church proceeding of loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To what ende?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſte, that the name of God and of Chriſt<note n="(3)" place="margin">Rom. 2.24. tit. 2.5.</note> be not euil ſpoken of and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched, by the euill ſuffered in the Church. Secondly, that the good be not<note n="(4)" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.6. 1. tim. 5.20.</note> corrupted, by the euill example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked. Thirdly, that the offenders<note n="(5)" place="margin">1. Cor. 5.5. 2. the. 3.14.</note> might be brought to repentance and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing God knoweth whereof we haue neede before we aſke: wherefore ſhould we pray?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſte, to ſtirre vp our ſelues to<note n="(1)" place="margin">Pſal. 105.4. &amp; 119.2.</note> ſeeke him. Secondly, to<note n="(2)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.41.58.76.</note> exerciſe our faith, in meditating vppon his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. Thirdly, that we maye diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge and vnload our conſciences in<note n="(3)" place="margin">Pſal, 55.22. 1. pet. 5.7.</note> caſting our cares into the boſome of God. Fourthly, that we teſtifie to our ſelues and to others, that we hope and ſeeke for all good thinges<note n="(4)" place="margin">Iam. 1.17. pſa. 145.15.16</note> from God alone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What things belong to true prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſte it is requiſite that we make our prayer to God<note n="(5)" place="margin">Pſa. 50.15. rom. 10.14. mat. 4.10.</note> onely through<note n="(6)" place="margin">Ioh. 14.13.14</note> Chriſt, and not to ſaints. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that we be inwardly touched with the neceſſitie<note n="(7)" place="margin">Rom. 8.26. 2. ioh. 5.14.</note> of the thinges that we aſke, hauing our mindes wholy<note n="(8)" place="margin">Pſa. 145.18.19. mat. 6.7.8.</note> bent there vpon, and not carryed away with any by thoughtes. Thirdly, that our prayers bee grounded vpon Gods<note n="(9)" place="margin">Math. 7.7. &amp; 21.22. mar. 11.24. 1. ioh. 5.25.</note> promiſes with full aſſuraunce that they ſhall be graunted, ſo farre as the Lorde doth know them to be meet and needful for vs. Fourthly, that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb facs="tcp:18910:24"/>
               <note n="(1)" place="margin">Lu. 18.1.2.3. rom. 12.12. 1. theſ. 5.17. mat. 15.12.</note> in prayer, although we haue not our requeſt at the firſte. Fiftly, that we aſke not thoſe things that we thinke good in our owne<note n="(2)" place="margin">Iam. 4.3.</note> fantaſie, but onely that which God<note n="(3)" place="margin">Rom. 8.26. 1. ioh. 14. mat. 6.9.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth vs to aſke of him, all which thinges bee contayned in the Lordes prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the Lordes prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our father which art in heauen, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy name. Thy kingdome come. Thy will be done in earth as it is in heauen. Giue vs this day our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread. And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. And lead vs not into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. But deliuer vs from euill. For thine is the kingdome the power and the glory for euer. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many principal parts are there of this prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſte a perſwaſion to pray in theſe wordes, Our father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.
<pb facs="tcp:18910:25"/>Secondly, the ſumme of praier contayned in the ſixe peticions. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, an aſſuraunce of that we praye for, contayned in the concluſion, for thine is kingdome, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What perſwaſion haue we in theſe wordes? Our father, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in that he is<note n="(1)" place="margin">Pſal. 103.13. 2. cor. 6.18.</note> a Father and not a Tyraunt, we are encouraged to come to him. Secondly, that he is our<note n="(2)" place="margin">Rom. 1.7. 1. cor. 1.3.</note> Father, and therefore loueth vs. Thirdly, that<note n="(3)" place="margin">Eſai. 66.1. acts. 7.48.</note> heauen is his throne, and therefore he is able to helpe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many partes are in the ſixe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticions?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They may be comprehended in two partes. The firſt three peticions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the glory of God. The ſecond, concerneth the neceſſity of man, ſet downe in the laſt three peticions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What deſireſt thou of God in the firſt peticion: halowed by thy name?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt I deſire of my heauenly father, that his name be halowed or ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Firſt in his excellent<note n="(1)" place="margin">Pſal. 113.2. &amp; 145.1.10.21. rom. 11.36. &amp; 16.27.</note> workes: which is, when we acknowledge his mercye, wiſedome, iuſtice, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and that he alone worketh all thinges, and that onely the Lorde God <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in honour, all other ſet a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Secondly, that his name bee glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Godly<note n="(2)" place="margin">Mat. 5.16. 1. cor. 10.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> life and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What deſire you of God in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond petition? Thy kingdome come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond peticion we deſire that God his kingdome may come, that is: that he will ſhew him ſelfe, to be king<note n="(3)" place="margin">Math. 3.2. &amp; 13.31. 2. the. 3.5.</note> (<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Church, in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and increaſing the number of the faithfull.<note n="(4)" place="margin">Mat. 9.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. ephe. 6.19.</note> By thruſting forth labourers into his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and in bleſſing their labours ſuppreſſing<note n="(5)" place="margin">Rom. 16.20. 2. the. 3.2.</note> the rage of wicked tyrants, and that he wit <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> kingdome ſeuerally, in euery <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="(6)" place="margin">Rom. 6.6. &amp; 8.10. 1. ioh 3.9.</note> killing ſinne in vs, and al
<pb facs="tcp:18910:26"/>worldly care, and renuing vs to righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What deſire you in the third petici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Thy will be done in earth as it is in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third peticion we deſire that Gods<note n="(1)" place="margin">Luk. 22.42. 1. pet. 4.19. 1. ioh. 2.17.</note> wil may be done, that in, that wee may willingly in all thinges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne our ſelues to Gods will, without murmuring or grudging, and walke in true<note n="(2)" place="margin">Rom. 12.2. eph. 5.17.</note> obedience of his will, after the example of the<note n="(3)" place="margin">Pſal. 103.20.</note> Angels in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doe you aſke in the fourth pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticion?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fourth peticion, we pray, that he will giue vs (walking faithfully in our calling) our dayly<note n="(4)" place="margin">Gen. 3.19. 2. theſ. 3.8. pſal. 146.7.</note> bread: What is all thinges needfull for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and nouriſhment of our bodies in this natural life. And here we haue to learne, firſt that we doe not thinge theſe earthly <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, That ſet <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18910:26"/>the nouriſhment and preſeruation of our bodies, as of our ſelues,<note n="(1)" place="margin">Pſal. 145.16. Pſal 146.7. mat. 6.32.33.</note> for they are the giftes of God. Secondly, that we ought to ſeek them at<note n="(2)" place="margin">Gen. 28.20. pſa. 107.5.6.</note> the hands of God. Thirdly, that we ought to be<note n="(3)" place="margin">Iohn. 6.11. 1. tim. 4.4.</note> thankful to God for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What deſire you in the fift peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fift peticion, we pray that our ſinnes may be<note n="(4)" place="margin">Pſal. 32.1. dan. 9.19. hoſe. 14.2.</note> forgiuen vs, and that he will not <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aye to our charge our ſinnes and offences, nor the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to them: but that he will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the death and paſſion of<note n="(5)" place="margin">3. Pet. 1.19. 1. ioh. 1.7.</note> Chriſt, as the full ſatiſfaction for our ſinnes, and that we may hereof haue full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce in our conſciences, that the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of our ſinnes, is fully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged in Chriſt, and therefore freely forgiuen vs, as ſurely as we do feele that we<note n="(6)" place="margin">Math. 6.14. mar. 11.25. ephe. 4.3<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> forgiue others. And that we loue one an other, from the bottom of our heartes,<note n="(7)" place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.39.44 45. rom. 12.17.19.20.</note> all deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, ſet aſide.</p>
            <p>And here we haue alſo <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:18910:27"/>Firſt, that all<note n="(1)" place="margin">Eſai. 53.6. iom. 3.23.</note> men are ſinners. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that,<note n="(2)" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.8.9.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> can not ſatiſfie, but muſt ſeeke forgiuenes. Thirdly that none can forgiue ſinnes,<note n="(3)" place="margin">Eſay. 43.25. mar. 3.7.</note> but God only. Fourthly, that to<note n="(4)" place="margin">Math. 6.15. mar. 11.26.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man that will not forgiue <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> no forgiuenes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doe you demaund in the ſixt peticion? lead vs not into temptation: but deliuer vs from euill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſixt peticion we pray, that we be not deliuered to the power<note n="(5)" place="margin">Rom 16.20.</note> of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than: and that we be no further<note n="(6)" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.13.</note> tempted, then God giue vs power to beare and ouercome. And that he<note n="(7)" place="margin">Eph. 6.10.16.17. iam. 4.7. 1. pet. 5.9.</note> would deliuer vs, and make vs victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ouer ſinne and the Deuill. And here me haue to learne: firſt that all Chriſtians are in<note n="(8)" place="margin">Eph. 6.10.12 &amp; 18. 1 pet. 5.8.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and haue need to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> watch and pray. Secondly, that we are all<note n="(9)" place="margin">Pro 20.34. iere. 10.23. rom. 7.19.</note> weak and haue need of helpe. Thirdly, that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="(10)" place="margin">Iob. 1.2. math. 8.;3</note> can do nothing vnleſſe the Lords giue him leaue. Fourthly, that the Lorde is our deliuerer<note n="(11)" place="margin">Pſal. 54.19. &amp; 146.7.19.</note> out of all temptations.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18910:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Thine is the kingdome, the power, and the glory, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, theſe wordes ſhould<note n="(1)" place="margin">1. Chro. 29.3. rom. 11.36.</note> kindle our heartes to deſire the glory of God. Secondly, that our prayers be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon none<note n="(2)" place="margin">Pſal. 50.15. mat. 4.10.</note> but God only. Third<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, that his kingdome, power and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: is almighty and euerlaſting,<note n="(3)" place="margin">1. Chr. 29.10 11,12. reuel. 4.10.11</note> and that he onely is to be honoured and glorified. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> confirmed in the aſſuraunce of that we praye for. And in this word <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is expreſſed our feruent <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="(4)" place="margin">Rom. 16.27. 1. pet. 5.1. reuel. 7.12.</note> is obtayn thoſe thinges which we aſke of God: and our hope is confirmed, that thoſe thinges which wee aſke are graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs: by which our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are pacified. And ſo we ende our prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where finde you that there ought to be any ſuch examination?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:28"/>
            <p>I find that our Sauiour Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he had taught his Diſciples, did againe<note n="(1)" place="margin">Mat 13.51. &amp; 16.13 &amp; 17.25. ioh. 6.5.</note> examine them: howe they had profited. And in examining them, did teach them further.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18910:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
